{"tossups": [{"question": "The Alma-Ata Protocols were signed in the wake of this event, and one man\u2019s proclamation of the\u201cSinatra Doctrine\u201d encouraged this event. One leader was imprisoned in his dacha at Foros prior to this event, which led to the formation of the CIS. The ascension of Boris Yeltsin marked the end of, for ten points, what event which led to the independence of Ukraine, Belarus, and many other countries?", "answer": "<b> Dissolution</b> of the<b> USSR</b> (accept synonyms for dissolution, accept<b> Soviet Union</b> for USSR; do not accept or prompt \u201cfall of the Berlin Wall\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Jonathan Baldwin Turner advocated for the creation of more of these institutions in the 1850s. The Smith-Lever Act was implemented to allow greater cooperation between these institutions and their surroundings, and HBCUs are examples of these institutions that were established for African-Americans after the Civil War. The Morrill Land-Grant Acts set aside land for the creation of these institutions, including one in Champaign, Illinois. For ten points, name these educational institutions, including Iowa State, Cornell, and MIT.", "answer": "<b> college</b>s (or<b> universities</b>; prompt on (public) schools)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader is depicted in the Catalan Atlas sitting on a throne and inspecting a gold nugget. This leader commissioned the Djinguereber [jin-gah-ray-bear] Mosque and Sankore University, both located in Timbuktu, and he caused a massive deflation of the price of gold in Cairo while on an extravagant Hajj to Mecca. For ten points, name this Mali emperor, or Mansa, who ruled from 1312 to 1327.", "answer": "Mansa<b> Musa</b> (or<b> Musa I</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This composer wrote a cantata beginning \u201cEternal source of light divine\u201d to celebrate Queen Anne\u2019s birthday. This composer wrote four coronation anthems, including<em> Zadok the Priest</em>, for another British monarch who asked this composer to write a piece celebrating the end of the War of the Austrian Succession. For ten points, name this Baroque composer of the<em> Music for the Royal Fireworks</em>, as well as the oratorio<em> Messiah</em>.", "answer": "George Frideric<b> Handel</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This organization donated the<em> SMS Goeben</em> to the Ottoman Navy, and a rebellion by this organization in Kiel led to the end of the empire it served. Alfred Tirpitz sought to reform this organization, which used wolfpacks to attack British convoys. This organization made heavy use of the doctrine of unrestricted submarine warfare, and was led through WWII by Admiral Karl D\u00a8onitz. For ten points, name this navy which used U-Boats during the two World Wars.", "answer": "<b> German Navy</b> (prompt on Kreigsmarine, prompt on Reichsmarine) Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One speech given in this location referenced a John Magee poem, noting that seven people, including Ronald McNair, had \u201cslipped the surly bonds of Earth to touch the face of God.\u201d After a meeting in this location, Elvis Presley was given a badge for the Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs. A photograph taken in this location shows a child playing beneath the Resolute Desk, Richard Nixon called the<em> Apollo</em> <em>11</em> astronauts from, for ten points, what room located in the West Wing in the White House?", "answer": "<b> Oval Office</b> (prompt on West Wing and White House before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Leo Strauss argued that \u201cModern\u201d philosophy began with this man, who used Hannibal and Scipio Africanus as examples of brutal rulers. The author of<em> Ab Urbe Condita</em>, the Roman historian Livy, inspired a discourse by this author, who encourages the title figure of another work to emulate both the lion and the fox. \u201cIt is better to be feared than loved\u201d according to, for ten points, what Italian author of <em>The Prince</em>?", "answer": "Niccolo<b> Machiavelli</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "The Sullivan-Hoey law was passed in response to this incident. This event helped spur the growth of the ILGWU after the \u201cUprising of 20,000.\u201d This event started on the eighth floor of the Asch building, whose main exits were locked on orders of the owners, Max Blanck and Isaac Harris. 146 mostly-female garment workers died in, for ten points, what 1911 fire that consumed a New York sweatshop?", "answer": "<b> Triangle Shirtwaist</b> Factory Fire", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The United Kingdom almost joined this war after its fishermen were mistaken for warships in Dogger Bank by the Baltic Fleet. This war\u2019s aftermath led to Sergei Witte\u2019s [VIT-uh\u2019s] industrializtion efforts and the October Manifesto. It began inconclusively at Port Arthur, and was ended, with Theodore Roosevelt\u2019s assistance, by the Treaty of Portsmouth. For ten points, name this 1904-05 war between countries led by Tsar Nicholas II and Emperor Meiji.", "answer": "<b> Russo-Japanese</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Ion Pacepa, a 3-star general from this nation, defected to the United States during the Cold War, the highest-ranking Eastern bloc defection. This nation was joined with Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia in the Little Entente. One leader of this country succeeded Georghe Georghiu-Dej, and promulgated the July Theses; that leader and his wife were executed by firing squad on Christmas Day, 1989. For ten points, name this Eastern European country that was ruled by Nicolae Ceausescu [cho-CHESS-ku].", "answer": "<b> Romania</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The \u201cPlan West\u201d defensive scheme was unsuccessful during this campaign, and the Battle of Mokra during this campaign saw a cavalry charge successfully repel a tank advance. The Gleiwitz incident was used as a pretense by one side in this conflict to launch an attack, and the \u201cPhony War\u201d followed this action. The Free City of Danzig was annexed after, for ten points, what September 1st, 1939 offensive that marked the beginning of World War II?", "answer": "<b> Invasion</b> of<b> Poland</b> (prompt on World War II)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A museum named for Tuol Sleng commemorates those who died at the hands of this party after it won a civil war against Lon Nol. This party called its state Democratic Kampuchea, and it created tens of thousands of mass graves in the Killing Fields. For ten points, name this communist movement led by Pol Pot which ruled Cambodia in the 1970s.", "answer": "<b> Khmer Rouge</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s village of Ba Chuc was the site of a Cambodian massacre in that invasion.", "answer": "Socialist Republic of<b> Vietnam</b> (do not accept references to a divided North or South Vietnam, as this is post-unification)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s son James was killed by members of the Shawnee tribe, sparking Dunmore\u2019s War, and his son Israel was killed at the Battle of Blue Licks. This friend of Simon Kenton was briefly captured by Blackfish in 1778. A John Filson book created a series of myths about, for ten points, what frontiersman who helped settle Kentucky by blazing a trail through the Cumberland Gap?", "answer": "Daniel<b> Boone</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This country repelled the forces of Eleftherios Venizelos after they landed at Smyrna, in accordance with the Treaty of (+) Sevres that divided this country\u2019s immediate predecessor. This country\u2019s independence was guaranteed by the Treaty of Lausanne, and it saw reforms based on the Six Arrows of its first leader, who adopted Latin script, banned (*)</b> fezzes, and deposed the Sultan. For ten points, name this country, formed from the remnants of the Ottoman Empire by Kemal Ataturk, which has its capital at Ankara.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Turkey</b> (do not accept or prompt on the Ottoman Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In one speech, this man compared interviewing Jesse Jackson to boxing a glacier, then told his audience, \u201cenjoy that metaphor, because your grandchildren will have no idea what a glacier is.\u201d A character played by this man frequently used the nickname (+) \u201cPapa Bear\u201d</b> <b>to refer to Fox News host Bill O\u2019Reilly.</b> <b>\u201cAmericans for a Better Tomorrow, Tomorrow\u201d</b> <b>was a super PAC founded by this comedian, who coined the term (*)</b> \u201ctruthiness\u201d on the first episode of his namesake spin-off of<em> The Daily Show</em>. For ten points, name this former host of a<em> Report</em> on Comedy Central, the current host of CBS\u2019s<em> Late Show</em>.", "answer": "Stephen<b> Colbert</b> [kohl-BAYR]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>The novels</b><em><b> No Longer Human</b></em><b> and</b><em><b> The Setting Sun</b></em><b> are characteristic of the \u201cI-novel\u201dstyle developed in this country in the 1940s. The short story \u201cPatriotism\u201d follows the</b> <b>aftermath of a coup in this nation; the same author wrote a fascist play, (+)</b> <em><b>My Friend</b></em> <em><b>Hitler</b></em><b>, before his death in an attempted coup d\u2019etat in 1970. The burning of the (*)</b> Golden Pavilion in this country inspired a 1956 novel narrated by Mizoguchi. The authors Osamu Dazai and Yukio Mishima are from, for ten points, what Asian country?", "answer": "<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This successor of Johnny Torrio claimed that a war wound, rather than Frank Gallucio\u2019s</b> <b>knife, inspired his nickname. Despite ordering the (+)</b> <b>knife, inspired his nickname. Despite ordering the (+)</b> <b>killings of dozens of men, probably</b> <b>including the seven killed in the St.</b> <b>Valentine\u2019s Day Massacre, he was only convicted of</b> <b>Valentine\u2019s Day Massacre, he was only convicted of</b> <b>(*)</b> tax evasion. For ten points, name this man, nicknamed \u201cScarface,\u201d who led the Chicago mob during Prohibition.", "answer": "Alphonse Gabriel \u201cAl\u201d<b> Capone</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s government was defeated by a promise to create a universal National Health</b> <b>Service under Labour Party leader Clement (+)</b> <b>Attlee, whom this man suggested would</b> <b>need \u201ca Gestapo\u201d to implement his plans. This man proclaimed \u201cI have nothing to offer but blood, (*) </b> toil, tears, and sweat\u201d upon taking office in 1940, shortly before Germany began \u201cthe Blitz\u201d against his country. For ten points, name this British Prime Minister during World War II.", "answer": "Winston<b> Churchill</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Peter Williamson, one of these people, was captured by Native Americans and returned to England as \u201cIndian Peter\u201d in the 18th century. A practice known as \u201cblackbirding\u201d is sometimes used to (+) acquire these people. A \u201credemptioner\u201d policy allowed these people to buy their freedom after a determined (*) </b> number of years, commonly seven. For ten points, name this practice where people paid for passage to the New World in exchange for a period of forced service, which was banned with slavery by the 13th Amendment.", "answer": "<b> Indentured servant</b>s (accept word forms; prompt on partial, do not prompt or accept\u201cslaves\u201d) ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>These objects were the specialty of Jean Bureau, who used them to win the Battle</b> <b>of Castillon. The ribaldi was a primitive type of these objects, and the Hungarian</b> <b>engineer Orban was credited with introducing these objects to the (+)</b> <b>Ottoman</b> <b>Empire, where it made Greek Fire obsolete. These objects, which included culverins</b> <b>and (*)</b> falconets, were used against the Theodosian Walls in a 1453 siege. Great bombards were, for ten points, what type of large gun, used to win the Siege of Constantinople?", "answer": "<b> cannon</b>s (accept<b> artillery</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}